<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesties most gracious speech to both houses of Parliament, at the opening of the Parliament at Oxford, Monday the 21st of March, 1680/1. Published by his Majesties command.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02096</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3164</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171248</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52612077</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52612077</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179362</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02096)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179362)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2786:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesties most gracious speech to both houses of Parliament, at the opening of the Parliament at Oxford, Monday the 21st of March, 1680/1. Published by his Majesties command.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Re-printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson, printer to his most sacred majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title vignette: royal arms.</note>
                  <note>Initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Ms. annotations on title page and verso of final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: blurred print, print show-through with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179362:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->
            <p>His Majeſties Moſt Gracious SPEECH To both Houſes of PARLIAMENT, At the opening of the PARLIAMENT At <hi>Oxford, Monday</hi> the 21<hi rend="sup">ſt</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1680/1.</p>
            <p>P<gap reason="illegible" extent="8 letters">
                  <desc>〈8 letters〉</desc>
               </gap> by <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Majeſties Command.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="6 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊◊◊◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Re-printed by the Hir of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to His moſt Sacred <hi>Majeſty,</hi> Anno <hi>DOM.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:179362:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:179362:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <head>His Majeſties MOST GRACIOUS SPEECH To both HOUSES of PARLIAMENT, At the Opening of the PARLIAMENT at <hi>Oxford;</hi> 
               <date>Monday the 21<hi rend="sup">ſt</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 168<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</date>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lorde and Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He unwarrantable Proceedings of the laſt Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, were the occaſion of My parting with the laſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. For I, who will neyer uſe Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment My Self, am reſolved not to ſuffer it in others. I am unwilling to mention particulary, becauſe I am d<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rou<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to forget faults. But whoſoever ſhall <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ly conſider what Offers I have formerly made, and what Aſſurances I renewed to the laſt Parliament, how I recommended nothing ſo much to them, as the Alliances I had made for preſervation of the general Peace in Chriſtendom, and the further exanimation of the Popiſh Plot, and how I deſired their Advice and Aſſiſtance cancerning the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Tangi<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> and ſhall then reflect upon the ſtrange un<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>able <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de to ſuch Propoſitions, by men that were called toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Conſult; perſhaps may wonder more, that I had patience ſo long, th<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n that at laſt I grew weary of their Proceedings.</p>
            <p>I have thought it neceſſary to ſay thus much to you, That I may not have any new Occaſion given Me to remember more of the late M<gap reason="illegible" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>ges. If is as much My Intereſt, and ſhall be as much My Care as yours, to preſerve the Liberty of the Subject, becauſe the C<gap reason="illegible" extent="7+ letters">
                  <desc>〈7… letters〉</desc>
               </gap> never be ſafe when that is in danger. And I would have you likewiſe be convinc'd, that neither your Liberties nor Properties can ſubſiſt long, when the juſt Rights and Prerogatives of the Crown are invaded, or the Honour of the Govern<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> brought low, and into Diſreputation.</p>
            <p>I let you ſee by My calling this Parliament ſo ſoon, that no Irregularities in Parliaments ſhall make Me out of Love with Them; and by this Means offer you another Opportunity of providing for Our Security here, by giving that Countenance and Protection to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179362:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
Our Neighbours and Allies, which you cannot but know They ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from Us, and extreamly ſtand in need of at this inſtant; and at the ſame time give one Evidence more, that I have not neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed My part, to give that general Satisfaction and Security, which, by the Bleſſing of God, may be attained, if you, on your parts, bring ſuitable Diſpoſitions towards it: And that the juſt Care you ought to have of Religion, be not ſo managed and improv'd into unneceſſary Fear<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as to be made a pretence for changing the Foundations of the Government.</p>
            <p>I hope the Example of the ill Succeſs of former Heats, will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you to a better Temper, and not ſo much to Inveigh againſt what is paſt, as to Conſider what is beſt to be done in the preſent Conjuncture.</p>
            <p>The further proſecution of the Plot, the Tryal of the Lords in the Tower, the Providing a more ſpeedy Conviction for Recuſants; and, if it be practicable, the Ridding Our ſelves quite of all of that Party, that have any conſiderable Authority and Intereſt amongſt Them, are Things, though of the higheſt Importance, that hardly need to be recommended to you, they are ſo obvious to every mans Conſideration, and ſo neceſſary for Our Security. But I muſt needs deſire you not to lay ſo much weight upon any one Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent againſt Popery, as to determine, that all other are inefectual: And among all Your Cares for Religion, remember, that without the Safety and Dignity of the Monarchy, neither Religion nor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty can be preſerved.</p>
            <p>What I have formerly, and ſo often declared touching the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I cannot depart from. But to remove all reaſonable Fears that may ariſe from the poſſibility of a Popiſh Succeſſor's coming to the Crown, if means can be found, that, in ſuch a Caſe, the Adminiſtration of the Government may remain in Proteſtant Hands, I ſhall be ready to hearken to any ſuch Expedient, by which the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion might be Preſerv'd, and the Monarchy not deſtroy'd.</p>
            <p>I muſt therefore earneſtly recommend to you, to provide for the Religion and the Government together, with regard to one another, becauſe they ſupport each other: And let Us be united at home, that We may recover the Eſteem and Conſideration We uſed to have abroad.</p>
            <p>I conclude with this one Advice to you, That the Rules and Meaſures of all your Votes, may be the known and eſtabliſhed Laws of the Land, which neither can, nor ought to be departed from, nor ch<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng'd, but by Act of Parliament: And I may the more fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bly require, That you make the Laws of the Land your Rule, becauſe I am reſolv'd they ſhall be Mine.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:179362:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
